Guide to the Jesuit Missionary Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jesuit Missionary Collection
1671-1749
WA MSS S-1143
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(2 boxes)
The collection documents the history of the Jesuit missions in Mexico. Letters by the padres, the Visitador Alvaro Flores de Sierra, and military leaders discuss the Seri Indian attacks on the missions and the need for military protection. Documents addressed to Juan de Yturberoaga, Procurador of the Province of New Spain, concern the distribution of supplies to the missions and their administration. Material also describes the difficulty of transporting cattle in the region.
Jesuits
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Unspecified; please consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection of 154 documents spans the dates November 8, 1671 through December 18, 1749. The documents were created in various sites throughout Sonora and Sinaloa, Mexico, and in Arizona. They comprise 289 pages and fall into three related groups. The first group (entries 1 through 16 on the list) consists of 16 letters by various Jesuit missionaries, by the Visitador Alvaro Flores de Sierra, and by military leaders. They were written between November 8, 1671 and December 22, 1672 and are arranged chronologically. The letters concern recent attacks by the Seri Indians on Jesuit missions and villages and discuss the need for improved military protection.
The second group of manuscripts consists of 119 letters and documents addressed to Juan de Yturberoaga, Procurador of the Province of New Spain, concerning the distribution of supplies to the Jesuit missions as well as other administrative matters. The letters, which were written between December 5, 1707 and September 30, 1710 are arranged in alphabetical order by author. They are described in entries 17 through 49.
The third group of mansucripts consists of 19 letters written between October 23 and December 18, 1749. In the letters, various authors describe the problem of Seri attacks on the missions and settlements. The first document in the group (entry 50) describes in detail the many obstacles to transporting cattle in the region. The letters are arranged in alphabetical order by author and consist of entries 50 through 65. A list of names that appear in the collection:
Abendano, Juan de
Albarado, Ygnacio de
See: Alvarado, Ignacio de
Aldrete, Florencio de
Almanza, Miguel Xavier de, 1676-1725
Almonacir, Juan de
Almonazir, Juan de
See: Almonacir, Juan de
Alvarado, Ignacio de
Alvares, Esteban
Alvares, Juan
Anaya, Juan de
Aragon, Juan Antonio de
Arias, Antonio
Astina, Antonio de
Baduinari, Lorenzo
Balthasar, Juan Antonio, 1697-1763
Bartyromo, Melchor de, 1663-
Bayerca, Fernando, 1663-1730
Bazaldua, Juan de
Benavides, Martin de
See: Venavides Martin de
Bentura Ferrer, Juan
See: Ventura Ferrer, Juan
Betancur, Juan de
Boltor, Juan
Brabo, Cristobal [?]
Buelna, Andres de
Campos, Augustin de
Canto, Luis del, 1634-1687
Castellanos, Juan de
Cortez, Jacinto
Cruz, Manuel de la
Cuellas, Quiler de
Diserino, Francisco
Egidiano, Andres
Encinas, Juan de
Estrada, Geronimo de
Estrada, Ignacio Xavier de
Estrada y Bocanegra, Antonio de
Eymer, Wenceslau, d. 1709
Fernandez Bello, Antonio
Fernandez Cabero, Juan
Fernandez Zalema, Joseph
Flores de Sierra, Alvaro, d. 1673
Garcia, Andres Xavier
Garcia, Nicolas
Garcia Ramon, Alonso
Garfias, Bernardo de
Genusque, Daniel
See: Januske, Daniel
Gilg, Adamo, 1653-
Gonzalez, Manuel, d. 1730?
Goyeneche, Juan Francisco de
Guerrero, Joseph
Guillercagh, Cornelio
Gutierrez, Bernabe Fernando
Gutierrez, Francisco
Haller, Juan Baptista
Herrera, Antonio de
Huter, Juan de
Januske, Daniel
Kappus, Marcos Antonio, 1657-1717
Kino, Eusebio Francisco, 1644- 1711
Landa, Juan Antonio
Leal, Antonio
Lizardi, Andres de
Loaysa, Baltasar Xavier de
Lopez Rendon, Joseph
Maldonado, Augustin
Mancuso, Luis
Marin, Antonio
Marino, Ignacio Maria
Marras, Daniel Angelo, 1629-1689
Mesa, Joseph de, d. 1749
Minutuli, Geronimo, 1669-ca. 1710
Miranda, Thomas
Molina, Basilio Xavier de
Montane, Juan Joseph
Montt Vio, Ambrosio Juan
Mora, Francisco Xavier de, 1662-1720
Morantes, Pedro
Moya, Sebastian de
Mungia Villela, Juan de
Nava, Diego Manuel de
Nayduri, Lorenzo
Neumann, Joseph, 1648-1732
Noriega, Francisco Xavier de
Ordaz, Manuel de
Oro, Nicolas de
Otermin, Antonio de
Palazuelos, Panta Leon de
Pallares, Joseph de
Peraza, Joseph, d. 1709
Perera, Nicolas de
Perez Arroyo, Francisco
Pistoya, Geronimo
Protho, Pedro, d. 1730
Proto, Pedro
See: Protho, Pedro
Ramirez de Castro, Matheo
Ramirez Fenorca, Atanasio
Reynaldos, Pedro
Rioja, Martin de
Rivera, Joseph Joaquin de
Rivera, Juan Honorado de
Rodriguez Gallardo, Joseph Raphael
Rojas, Carlos de, 1702-1773
Romo de Vivar, Joseph
Ruiz, Gabriel
Salas y Cortez, Pedro
San Martin, Juan de
Sanches, Thomas
Sandoval, Felipe de
Segesser, Felipe, 1689-1762
Solchaga, Thomas de
Soto, Francisco Xavier de
Soto Mayor, Andres de
Tagle de Bustamante, Francisco Antonio
Toral, Joseph, d. ca. 1763
Tovar, Manuel de
Valdes, Gregorio
Valencia Betancur, Manuel de
Vega, Bernardo de la
Venavides, Martin de
Ventura Ferrer, Juan
Villafana, Nicolas de, 1638-
Villafane, Nicolas de
See: Villafana, Nicolas de
Vitoria, Alonso de
Yling, Guillermo
Yragorri, Roque de
Yrazoqui, Juan de
Yturberoaga, Juan de
Zanuba, Aguerra [?] Geronimo
Zavala, Pedro Joseph de
Cattle -- Mexico; Missions -- Mexico; Seri Indians; Missionaries -- Spain; Vega, Bernardo de la; Yturberoaga, Juan de; Flores de Sierra, Alvaro, d. 1673; Jesuits -- Mexico
- Box and folder list, 1671 Nov 8-21
  - Marras, Daniel Angelo 1629-1689., 1671 Nov 8-21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Matape and other places [Sonora, Mexico]
    ALS to the Padres of the Mission of San Francisco
    de Borja
    4p., docketed 30.5 cm.
    Includes six ALS by Bernabe Francisco Gutierrez,
    B[altas]ar Xavier de Loaysa, Alonso de Vitoria,
    Quiler de Cuellas, Luis del Canto, and Juan
    Fernandez Cabero.
    The authors voice their frustration at not being
    able to get sufficient protection against the Seri
    Indians and discuss the urgency of putting them
    down before contempt of the Spanish spreads to
    other tribes.
  - Diserino, Francisco, 1671 Nov 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Pl. de Tuvaca [i.e. Tubac, Arizona]
    ALS to Vis[itador] Alv[ar]o Flores de Sierra
    2p., docketed 31 cm.
    Diserino and Padre Andres Egidiano respond to
    points raised in a visit and/or letter of the
    Visitador asking that he transmit their request
    to the Provincial that the Captain subdue the
    Seris. They describe the disorder caused by the
    non-Christian Indians and state that the Captain's
    only effort at subduing them did more harm than
    good.
  - Soto, Francisco Xavier de, 1671 Dec 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Hures [i.e. Ures, Sonora, Mexico]
    ALS to Daniel Angelo Marras
    3p., docketed 21.5 cm.
    Describes violence against the Nacameri Indians
    on the part of the Seris and requests Marras's
    assistance as head of the mission. Soto says that
    he wants to help the Nacameris and if necessary
    die with them.
  - Betancur, Juan de, 1671 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sonora [Mexico]
    Letter to Alvaro Flores de Sierra signed by Juan
    de Betancur, Juan de Huter, and Cornelio Guillercagh
    6p., docketed 29.5 cm.
    General Ramirez de Castro is mistaken concerning
    the efficacy of the entrada of Capt. Andres de
    Vuelna [i.e. Buelna]. Because there were only
    twelve soldiers under orders not to enter Seri
    country, the Seri show open contempt for them,
    killing Christian Indians particularly where the
    soldiers are, knowing they will not be followed
    and punished. This attitude is in danger of
    spreading to other tribes. Those that are barely
    Christian, such as the Yaqui, might revert; they
    have celebrated in their dances the Spaniards'
    fear of the Seris. The only solution is to send
    out the whole fort; the padres are willing to pay
    the expenses of the attack.
  - Betancur, Juan de, 1671 Dec 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    LS to Capt. D. Juan Francisco de Goyeneche
    2p., docketed 21.5 cm.
    Reiterates claims he says he has already made to
    General Matheo Ramirez de Castro and Visitador
    Alvaro Flores de Sierra, that stationing a few
    soldiers has done more harm than good. What is
    needed is not a guard ( escolta ) but an entrada.
  - Soto, Francisco Xavier de, 1671 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    The Seri are depraved and perverse, with an
    ingrained hatred of Christianity. Because they
    have met with no resistance, they continue doing
    all the damage they want, and if not hindered,
    may achieve their objective of wiping out
    Christianity in their country. Remarks that the
    soldiers, whom he and Padre Cornelio Guillercagh
    provisioned, only served to kindle the flame
    higher ( encender mas el fuego ).
  - Flores de Sierra, Alvaro, d. 1673., 1672 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    [Toro? Sinaloa, Mexico]
    ALS to the Provincial
    3p., docketed 31 cm.
    The Seris are divided into hostile and friendly
    groups. The posting of soldiers has hindered
    dealing with either group. The presidio of
    Sinaloa is no more than a shadow ( no es mas que una sombra ).
  - Goyeneche, Juan Francisco de, 1672 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Toapa [i.e. Tuape] Sonora [Mexico]
    ADS
    Also signed by Andres de Buelna and Estevan
    Albares. [i.e. Esteban Alvares]. Numbers of troops
    and expenses of the entrada into Seri country.
  - Romo de Vivar, Joseph, 1672 Jan 7-21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    San Antonion de la Natividad, Sonora [Mexico]
    Contemporary copy of a transcription of testimony by
    eight witnesses before Capt. Joseph Romo de Vivar,
    substituting for the Alcalde Mayor of Sonora
    37p., docketed 31 cm.
    Describes hostile acts of the Seri Indians, and
    the entradas against them.
  - Guillercagh, Cornelio, 1672 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Opodepe [Sonora, Mexico]
    3p., docketed 30.5 cm.
    Explains the excessive expenses of the campaigns
    against the Seris and criticizes their ineffect-
    iveness and even negative effect.
  - Salas y Cortez, Pedro, 1672 Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    [Sonora? Mexico]
    ALS to his uncle Jacinto Cortez
    3p., docketed 30 cm.
    Reports having spoken to Capt. Juan de Encinas,
    who had received a letter from Padre Francisco
    Gutierrez of Tecoripa saying that the Yaqui
    Indians were challenging them to war. The
    commander of the presidio refused to do anything
    unless he heard from the Padre directly, so the
    captain went out on his own and "punished the
    aggressors" who had killed many Indians. Discusses
    the necessity of preventing a major uprising.
    Also contains a letter of Jacinto Cortez,
    1672 Feb 24, Torea, referring his nephew's letter
    to Alvaro Flores de Sierra, Visitador of the
    missions of Sinaloa and Sonora.
  - Otermin, Antonio de, 1672 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Villa [Sinaloa, Mexico]
    ALS to Padre Visitador Alvaro Flores de Sierra
    2p., docketed 30.5 cm.
    He does not want to send out the whole presidio
    in order to maintain protection for nearby settle-
    ments. He cites the Viceroy's orders not to enter
    Indian territory. He is willing to send some
    troops out and believes that one squadron should
    be enough.
  - Flores de Sierra, Alvaro, d. 1673., 1672 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Toro [Sinaloa, Mexico]
    ALS to Mi P[adre] Prov[incia]l
    2p., docketed 302 cm.
    Reports having just seen Capt. Antonio de Otermin,
    who gave new excuses ("and all of them really
    frivolous") for not having controlled the Seris.
    Lists other tribes that need to be subdued:
    Hiahaques (Yaquis?), Tecoripas, Tepaves, and
    Mobas.
  - Flores de Sierra, Alvaro, d. 1673., 1672 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    ALS to Genl. Antonio de Otermin
    2p., docketed 29 cm.
    Discusses warring tribes and says that the
    Viceroys' orders are not demanding enough to
    maintain the status quo; a vigorous campaign
    against the Seris is called for.
  - Otermin, Antonio de, 1672 Dec 5 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Sinaloa [Mexico]
    LS to Padre Visitador Alvaro Flores de Sierra
    His information from Sonora is that the Seris
    have been quiet and peaceful, and is surprised
    Flores says otherwise. He blames the trouble-
    making Indians for spreading rumors. He is
    following the Viceroys' orders which are to send
    out forces only in case of great and manifest
    necessity.
  - Flores de Sierra, Alvaro, d. 1673., 1672 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    LS to the Captain of Sinaloa [i.e. Antonio de
    Otermin]
    Scathing letter castigating Otermin for not doing
    his job in protecting the province.
  - Aldrete, Florencio de, 1709 Aug 24 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    N[uestr]a S[eno]ra del Pilar de Norogachic
    ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga
    Sends a list of supplics needed for the year and
    reports the deaths of Padres Wenceslas Eymer and
    Joseph Peraza.
    List signed by Aldrete and Antonio Arias.
  - Almanza, Miguel Xavier de, 1676-1725., 1709 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Sta. Maria del Populo [Sonora, Mexico], 1709 Mar 5
    - 2 ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga, the first accompanied by a list of supplies needed for the year 3p., addressed and docketed 31.5 cm. The list is signed by Almanza and Francisco Xavier de Mora, rector of the mission. The first letter transmits the list and specially requests an iron for baking hosts. The second letter transmits the money owed for the present year's supplies and requests that it be forwarded to Padre Marcos Antonio Kappus at Aribechi. Almanza was prevented from delivering it himself by an outbreak of smallpox.
  - Almonazir, Juan de, 1709 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    MEMORIA PARA MEXICO ... [ADS]
    1 p. 30 cm.
    Account of supplies needed.
    Also signed by Pedro Protho.
  - Alvares, Juan, 1709 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    [Villa de Sinaloa? Oguera? Mexico]
    ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga with list of supplies
    needed for 1710
    2p., addressed and docketed 31.5 and 21 cm.
    Discusses the poverty of the mission and makes a
    special request for medicines. Mentions an
    enclosure accompanying the letter from the
    Visitador Antonio de Herrera, but the probably
    does not refer to the accompanying list, which is
    signed by Alvares.
  - Bartyromo, Melchor de, 1663-, 1709 Feb 22 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Kucurpe [i.e. Cucurpe, Sonora, Mexico], 1709 Apr 13
    - 2 ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga, the first accompanied by a list of supplies needed for the year 3p., docketed 31 cm. Concern payments for previous year and requests for supplies including a head, hands, and garments for a "Lady of the Sorrows."
  - Bayerca, Fernando, 1663-1730., 1709 Feb (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Mision de San Miguel, Ures [Sonora, Mexico]
    ADS [List of supplies needed for the year]
    1p., docketed 30.5 cm.
    Also signed by Francisco Xavier de Mora, rector
    of the mission.
  - Castellanos, Juan de, 1709pre Jul 25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    San Geronimo, Sonora? Mexico]
    1p., addressed and docketed 30 cm.
    Request for supplies and money.
  - Estrada, Geronimo de, 1709 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Partido de los Remedios en la Sierra de S. Andres
    [Sonora, Mexico]
    needed for the year
    2p., docketed 31.5 cm.
    Has not yet received his last allotment and begs
    that it be expedited because the people of his
    area are poorer than others.
  - Estrada, Ignacio Xavier de, 1708 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - San Joseph de Temeychi, 1709 May 16
    - 2 ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga 3p., docketed 31-31.5 cm. The first letter discusses his debt to Padre Juan Baptista Haller of Tepomera [?]. He would pay him if he had the money, but the only thing he has in abundance is want. In the second letter he is grateful for pardon of the debt, but he already paid it. Complains of his poverty and of the wealth of the Tarahumara missions like that of Padre Joseph Neuman who gives nothing to the Province although he could afford to.
  - Gilg, Adamo, 1653-, 1709 Feb 5-Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Matape [Sonora, Mexico]
    3 ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga and list of supplies
    needed for Matape
    5p., docketed 30-30.5 cm.
    In the first letter he complains of being slighted
    by the administration in Mexico City, and asks to
    be transferred since they think he is useless. In
    a postscript he blames the "vile Atanasio Ramirez"
    if his previous letters have been delayed in being
    delivered. The other letters concern accounts and
    supplies, and include a request that holy
    paintings and stained glass windows be sent
    directly to the individual missions. Accompanied by: Atanasio Ramirez Fenorca letter, 1707 Dec 5.
  - Ramirez Fenorca, Atanasio, 1707 Dec 5 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Mexico [City, Mexico]
    DS
    Supplies delivered by Ramirez to Padre Nicolas de
    Villafana at Matape. Autograph signed note at
    bottom of page, dated 1709 Feb 14, Tecoripa,
    states that Villafana never paid this account.
  - Gonzalez, Manuel, d. 1730?, 1709 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Movas [i.e. Mobas, Sonora, Mexico]
    needed
    Requests supplies for the year and complains of
    past service. The memoria is approved and signed
    by Pedro Protho.
  - Herrera, Antonio, 1709 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Arizpe [Sonora, Mexico] ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga 2p. 30 cm. With attached note. Complains of padres who don't deliver what they promise, disputes and infighting, the difficulties of delivering supplies, and the inability of many padres to pay for them. Accompanied by an anonymous letter, 1709 Nov 28
    - Arizpe, to Herrera, 3p., concerning discrepancies in accounts and the need for keeping records of the sale of cattle from the missions.
  - Januske, Daniel, 1709 Feb 29 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Oposura [Sonora? Mexico], 1709 Mar 11
    - ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga, with list of supplies needed for 1709 3p., docketed 21 cm. He is deeply disappointed that the black vestment he requested was not sent.
  - Kappus, Marcos Antonio, 1657-1717., 1709 Mar 6-Apr 12 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Aribetzi
    3 ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga with lists of supplies
    7p., docketed 31 cm.
    Concerning accounts and supplies. Thanks
    Yturberoaga for sending European newspapers and
    asks for spectacles for his failing eyesight.
  - Kino, Eusebio Francisco, 1644-1711., 1709 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    N[uestr]a S[enor]a de los Dolores [Sonora, Mexico]
    ADS with list of supplies needed for 1709
    2p. with separate docket sheet 31 cm.
    Also signed by Melchor de Bartyromo.
    Concerns accounts.
    Accompanied by list of the missions from which
    Yturberoaga received memorias for 1709.
  - Kino, Eusebio Francisco, 1644-1711., 1708 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Concerns accounts. Would like help at his mission
    in order to generate income for the province.
  - Leal, Antonio, 1709 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Quepaca, 1709 Apr 7
    - 2 ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga with list of supplies needed for 1709 4p., docketed 15.5-31 cm. Concerning accounts and supplies.
  - Lizardi, Andres de, 1709 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Banamitzi [i.e. Benamichi, Sonora, Mexico]
    needed for the district of Babiacora [i.e. Bavicora]
    for 1709
    3p., docketed 30-30.5 cm.
    Claims that his mission is not responsible for
    certain debts.
  - Mancuso, Luis, 1708 Oct 25- (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Sta. Maria de las Cuevas, 1709 Sep 11
    - 3 ALS and 1 LS to Juan de Yturberoaga with list of supplies needed for 1709 7p., docketed 30-31.5 cm. Regarding receipt of supplies and debt for which he disavows responsibility. Mentions that it has been seven years since he left Sicily, and reports the death of Padre Wenceslao [!] Eymer of the mission of Papigochi.
  - Marin, Antonio, 1709 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Utais
    needed and copy of Yturberoaga's reply
    Regarding accounts and conflicts between rich and
    poor missions.
  - Marino, Ignacio Maria, 1709 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Onapa
    needed for 1709
    signed by Pedro Proto
    5p., addressed and docketed 21 cm.
    Concerns accounts, and supplies recently received
    from Spain.
  - Minutuli, Geronimo, 1669-ca.1710., 1709 Feb 18 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Tubutama [Sonora, Mexico]
    2p., docketed 29.5-31.5 cm.
    Asks that iron implements for the Indians receive
    first priority in the next shipment of supplies
    to the mission.
    The list is also signed by Melchor de Bartyromo.
  - Molina, Basilio Xavier de, 1709 Mar 2 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Laquiarachi[c?] Sonora [Mexico]
    2p., docketed 20.5-31 cm.
    His is the poorest mission of all Sonora; he
    complains about not receiving limosna, and the
    dangers of travel in the heart of enemy country.
  - Moya, Sebastian de, 1709 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Santa Catalina, Sonora
    2p. 20.5-30.5 cm.
    Request for supplies.
  - Neuman, Joseph, 1648-1732., 1709 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Canichiqui, Sonora
    Letter to Juan de Yturberoaga
    2p. 30.5 cm.
    Needs of missions, with references to Tarahumara
    padres Tomas de Guadalajara, Ignacio de Estrada,
    and Juan Bautista Haller.
  - Pallares, Joseph de, 1709 Feb 27-Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Acontzi
    2 ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga with lists of supplies
    4p. 20-32 cm.
    Reports that Andres de Lizardi has left mission of
    Bavicora and has joined Padre Antonio Leal
  - Proto, Pedro, d. 1730., 1709 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Aribetzi, Sonora
    Concerns supplies and difficulties at various
    missions.
  - Rioja, Martin de, 1709 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    1p. 31.5 cm.
    He has promised twelve head of cattle to Padre
    Visitador Antonio de Herrera. He has no doubt that
    the latter, having experienced the missions first-
    hand, will inform the Procurador [Yturberoaga] and
    the Provincial as to the true condition of the
    missions and their wealth or lack thereof.
  - San Martin, Juan de, 1709 Mar 9 and 13 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Batuco, Sonora
    2 ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga
    4p., 21-31 cm.
    Concerns supplies.
  - Vega, Bernardo de la, 1710 Feb 12-Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    49 documents, the first signed by Vega and the
    rest signed by Nicolas Garcia
    52p., docketed 24.5-31 cm.
    Acknowledgments by the two masters of supply
    teams to Juan de Yturberoaga, Procurador of the
    Province of New Spain, of receipt of the
    supplies listed, for distribution to individual
    padres at missions in Sonora, Sinaloa, and
    Chihuahua.
  - Ventura Ferrer, Juan, 1709 Mar 3 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Saguaripa
    ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga, with list of supplies
    Concerns mission accounts.
    The list is signed by Pedro Protho.
  - Villafane, Nicolas, 1638- (Box 1, Folder 48)
    [1709, Sonora, Mexico]
  - Yling, Guillermo, 1708 Dec (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - S[anta] Ines de Chinipas, 1709 Mar 16
    - [Sonora? Mexico] 2 ALS to Juan de Yturberoaga and list of supplies needed for 1709 6p., 27-31 cm. In the first letter he makes various requests and complaints concerning supplies and debts. He asks for icons in silver and a missal bound in green or blue velvet with silver clasps. He mentions the arrival by sea of sixteen padres bound for the Phillipines and six for here, of which he asks three to be sent to his mission. In the second letter he complains that since the missions can't get supplies from the Province, they spend their money elsewhere and the money leaves the system. "If my Brother would send them what is necessary they would live grateful and there would be good money every year for the Province. Try it one year and you will see." Also mentions an epidemic.